<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter to Mr. Speaker Lenthall shewing that it were better to comply with His Maiesties offers and desires of peace, then to pursue the destruction of this land in the continuance of this unnatural warre.</title>
            <author>Warwick, Philip, Sir, 1609-1683.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67701</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W992</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R33564</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13523420</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13523420</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99939</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67701)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99939)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1559:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter to Mr. Speaker Lenthall shewing that it were better to comply with His Maiesties offers and desires of peace, then to pursue the destruction of this land in the continuance of this unnatural warre.</title>
                  <author>Warwick, Philip, Sir, 1609-1683.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99939:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> LETTER To M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>SPEAKER LENTHALL,</hi> SHEWING, THAT IT WERE BETTER TO COMPLY WITH HIS MAIESTIES OFFERS AND DESIRES OF <hi>PEACE,</hi> Then to purſue the Deſtruction of this Land, in the continuance of this unnaturall WARRE.</p>
            <p>Printed in Yeare, 1646.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:99939:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99939:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS cleane Creatures were eſteemed only thoſe that chew'd the Cudde, ſo is it amongſt men: ſure I am, did not too many men in this age, like the Horſe ruſh into the battell, not conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what it is they are doing, they could not have raiſed nor continued this unnaturall Warre as they do. You ſit amongſt that Party as a Moderator, therefore I direct this to you to thinke upon. I was one of thoſe that conceived your late great ſucceſſe promiſed ſome quiet (I cannot ſay Peace) to this miſerable Kingdom, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally when I read His Majeſties gracious Meſſage to the two Houſes But now I perceive you are a people that have <hi>Freti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um in manu,</hi> The oportunity, but not the heart to lay hold on the occaſion to ſtill this ſtorme. The ſad thoughts therefore of a Mourner for this Nation, and of a conſtant friend to you, (if you be at leaſure for ſuch ſtuffe) read in what followes.</p>
            <p>The firſt thing that came in my view was, from whence we were fallen. Here, I may ſay, I ſaw a very great Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but like a wordly pompe, my after thoughts ſoone clouded it. I lookt upon a lawfull King ſet in the glorious Throne of His Anceſtors, in His owne Perſon of eminent virtue, maſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by no bad inclination, but like him that S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaies ſeeks the maſtery, <hi>was temperate it all things.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 9. 25.</note> Nay when his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies were to wound him, they were forc'd to do it through other's ſides, and complain of ill Counſellors that they might, as much as in them lay, make him an ill King. And yet when ſome of thoſe Counſellors that had the envy of three Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon them, were to be condemned, it could not be by the Lawes in being, but an extorted new Bill, or an unheard of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:99939:3"/>Ordinance of Parliament, that muſt cut their thread of Life. And as theſe few dyed thus, ſo the reſt survived, not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed of <hi>Bribery, Oppreſſion, &amp;c.</hi> but queſtioned for opinions in Law: ſo as ſure the Subject that was thus ruled was little oppreſt; &amp; its fear'd our plenty made us collect our hard ſhips by Reaſoning, not Sence, which former times complain'd of. God knowes there is a great difference betwixt <hi>Specula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Evills</hi> which may happen, and <hi>Practicall,</hi> or <hi>Senſitive,</hi> which men doe feele. Beſides, what <hi>Government</hi> there that may not have ſomewhat ſaid againſt it?</p>
            <p>Doe you not remember the plenty and ſplendor the <hi>Jewes</hi> poſſeſt in <hi>Solomons</hi> time? And yet in his Sonnes (but marke it was becauſe God meant to viſit) a Declaration muſt come out,<note place="margin">1. King. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Your Father laid heavy burdens upon us.</hi> I am ſure they brought one upon themſelves, for they never had a good King after, and were led into Captivity, and never came out, which was not the lot of <hi>Judah,</hi>which clove to <hi>Rehoboam, Solomons</hi> Sonne. Doe you not call to mind what was written of good King <hi>Aſa,</hi> one charactered like his forefather <hi>David, &amp;c?</hi> and yet the words are,<note place="margin">2. Chron. 16.10.</note> 
               <hi>Aſa oppreſſed ſome of the People in his time.</hi> Doe you ſay, the World is not Round, becauſe there are ſome <hi>irregular Mountaines,</hi> Doe you not ſay, no <hi>Individuall Perſon is perfect in all things?</hi> Is it not a received opinion, <hi>he is best, that hath leaſt faults,</hi> not he that hath none? And muſt we then look for this <hi>perfection in Government</hi> only, or caſt off all <hi>obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aience?</hi> True it is, we can ſay there was <hi>illegall Ship mony;</hi> but converted to publick uſe we muſt acknowledge, (for give me leave to make a large Parentheſis, and rell you never a penny of that mony came to the Kings private: Nay, he ſpent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides it on the Navy, 40 or 50000 <hi rend="sup">l</hi> 
               <hi>per Annum</hi> of his owne Revenues) There were many <hi>Monopolies,</hi> its true, but in the hands of moſt of thoſe men, that have raiſed their hands a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their King ſince, and purſued Him to ſave themſelves.</p>
            <p>But enough of this: Next I ſaw as hopefull an Iſſue atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the <hi>Throne,</hi> and ſecuring the ſucceſſion of it as ever this <hi>Kingdome</hi> was bleſt with. And I cannot doubt (what ever threatens) but they were borne for the happineſſe of this
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:99939:3"/>Nation, and to poſſeſſe the <hi>Splendor</hi> of their owne <hi>Birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rights;</hi> And ſure, where <hi>Ingratitude</hi> dwells not, the Royall Perſon that brought ſuch fruit cannot want her due reverence.</p>
            <p>Then I looktupon the <hi>Profeſſion</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian Religion</hi> in this <hi>Church:</hi> A Conſiderative man muſt acknowledge it. <hi>Apoſtolick</hi> and <hi>Primitive.</hi> It wore <hi>Chriſts ſeamleſſe garment,</hi> more then any Church in the World, for the Rule of her <hi>Faith</hi> was the <hi>Word of God,</hi> and that (in difficult places under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood (which God knowes though they be many, yet concern few perſons, for their is enough without diſpute, that if be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved and practiſed, ſhall make private men ſaſe) as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded from the <hi>Primitive times.</hi> She proved not her truth by her oppoſition to either <hi>Romaniſt, Hereticke,,</hi> or <hi>Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke,</hi> thought it not ſufficient argument to prove ſhe was true, becauſe another was falſe, for ſhe was acquainted, that moſt commonly too warme diſputants, are often as diſtant from truth, as they are differing from each others opinion. Her <hi>Common Service</hi> or <hi>Liturgy,</hi> which She impoſed on none for their <hi>Private Devotion,</hi> but preſcribed for the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity of the publicke,</hi> was Syſteme of all <hi>Practicall Divinity,</hi> and She made the <hi>Life of Chriſt</hi> the Calendar of her yeare, for ſo did it buſy her Diſciples, that in every one year of their lives, they commemorated all their Saviour did in his: The matter and words of it were all Scripture phraſes, or ſence, and ſuch as without all Controverſie have been underſtood ſo by the learned Men of all differing profeſſions, untill a ſort of <hi>Enthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſts,</hi> queſtioned ſome few (but by them miſunderſtood) paſſages herein: So as it may be ſaid, <hi>God was ſerved in this Land, in Truth, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, Decency, and Honour.</hi> And as this bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Reformation</hi> was made by the <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Clergy,</hi> with the marke of Authority, and not the brand of Tumult, ſo it was admitted in to and confirmed ſo by the Lawes of the Land, that thoſe that will overthrow the <hi>Church,</hi> muſt ravell the whole <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> and if it be poſſible, make us more miſerable them we are at preſent.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Lawes of this Land,</hi> when I conſider how abſolute a <hi>Monarch</hi> the King was, Power of making <hi>Warre</hi> and <hi>Peace,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:99939:4"/>Iſſuing Commiſſions of Lievtenancy,</hi> (argument enough to whom the Sword was entruſted) <hi>Granting all Pardons</hi> and <hi>Diſpenſations, Coyning Mony,</hi> and <hi>Calling</hi> and <hi>Diſſolving Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, &amp;c.</hi> I could not but admire the wiſdome of our <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors,</hi> who had procured from their Kings ſuch reſtrictions, as that though they could not be denied to have the <hi>ſingle Power</hi> to all the former purpoſes inveſted in them alone, yet could they not have the free uſe of ſome of them without the generall Concurrence of the People; For though they could <hi>make Warre</hi> without their People, yet could they not <hi>Levy Mony</hi> to maintaine it without their Conſents: Though the King only was ſaid to make the Law, (notwithſtanding all can be ſaid againſt it, which is too long for a Letter) yet it was no Law, 'till the two Houſes of Parliament had conſented unto it. And ſo in ſome other things, whereby it may appeare the <hi>People ſought not to Eclipſe their Soveraignes due Honour, but to preſerve to themſelves a ſober Liberty.</hi> Here I cannot but ſadly contemplate how in all times ſome few. Perſons, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the pretence of <hi>Liberty for the People,</hi> have got the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage and preferment of having a ſhare in the rule of them. And Whether ſuch Changes bring eaſe, this is a time that the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt; man may have gained experience enough to inform him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; To you I need not quote Hiſtory to prove it, ſince you know nothing is more unqueſtionable. He that knew the danger of <hi>Innovation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 24.21.</note> cryes loud, <hi>My Son, meddle not with thoſe that love changes.</hi> And he that conſidered how natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men degenerate,<note place="margin">1. Pet .2.16.</note> gave it as a Precept, <hi>Make not your liberty at loake for Licentiouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well Sir, but <hi>Hinc illae Lachrimae,</hi> This was the ſowrce of our preſent miſeries, for upon the calling of this preſent Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, though the Subject in generall were never in a more plentifull condition at home, by reaſon of his MAJESTIES ſtrength at Sea, and their owne great Trade ſo conſiderable &amp; rich abroad, yet the Roule of greivances is preſented, and this Free People taught to beleive they were <hi>Iſſachers</hi> Aſſe, ready to couch betwixt her burthens; And fit for them to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend new Officers to their King, they might confide in. And
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:99939:4"/>what was theirſſue of it? A ſpeedy gracious and entire reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy afforded by his Majeſty (without any returne) to all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained off. Was it ſaid frequeney of Parliaments were wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting? A Trieniall Bill was granted, nay, with ſuch a Clauſe, that they might meet, if omitted to be called. Was it feared his Majeſties inclinations lay not to receive Counſell from that Body? He ſecures that, by granting ſuch Acts as diveſted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in poynt of Revenue, of a Regall ſubſiſtance, without a future conſtant good underſtanding betwixt Him and them: Witneſſe quitting Ship mony by a Bill, laying down His Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, and Impoſitions, and obliging himſelf to receive them only when granted to him by Act of Parliament. Did He not as I may ſay, impale all His <hi>Forreſts</hi> in narrow bounds, that were ſo extenſive before? Did He not ſecure His Subjects from being preſt, which was little though then, would have been an occaſion of ſo many thouſands of them to be ſoon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, imbruing their hands in each others bloud? Were there any <hi>Courts</hi> conceived to be grievous, and not taken away? was not the <hi>Starchamber</hi> of excellent uſe and known neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſubmitted to this fate? Was not the <hi>High-Commiſſion</hi> takes down, ſo us ſince there hath been no legall reſtraint or puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for <hi>Inceſt</hi> or <hi>Adultery?</hi> I'l not dwell upon repenting the Bill concerning the Court of <hi>Yorke,</hi> nor limiting the <hi>Councell Table, &amp;c.</hi> But I'l ſhut up all in this, That the King gave one aſſurance in all, when He Conſented to the Bill for not diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving this Parliament: That He intended wholly to throw Himſelfe upon the Affection and Love of His People.</p>
            <p>Me thinks now any man living ſhould be ready to ask me, What? after all this <hi>Purging,</hi> did the <hi>Stomack</hi> ſend up any <hi>Jealous Fumes to the head?</hi> yes, you know they did; and how for deſiring the ſame Iuſtice and forme of proceeding againſt ſome <hi>Members,</hi> whom He accuſed, which they had held againſt ſome others that they had formerly impeached, They taiſed ſuch popular Commotions, They drove Him from His Parliament: yet as if loth to part, willing to returne, whil'ſt He was at <hi>Hampton Court,</hi> and <hi>Windſor,</hi> what Gracious Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages did He ſend in Expoſtulation of that buſineffe, what
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:99939:5"/>acknowledgement offered He to make upon pretended <hi>Brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Priviledges,</hi> and could not be hearkned too. When He was forc'd to retire further, and when He was at <hi>Yorke,</hi> attended with ſo many Lords, what was the whole Conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations there, but by Meſſages from Himſelfe, Aſſurances from the Peeres about Him, that He ſought nothing more, but a good underſtanding with them.</p>
            <p>When the 19 <hi>Propoſitions</hi> came, that <hi>Dropſie</hi>-like thirſted after ſo much more, when it had bin fed ſo plentifully before. What were his condeſcentions? Did he not offer His Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellours ſhould take a larger Oath (then was propoſed) for maintaining not of any part, but the Whole Law? Did he not aſſure you, <hi>That there was no man ſo near him in place or affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, whom he would not leave to the Iuſtice of the Law?</hi> Was not all offered you could deviſe whereby Papiſts might be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to diſturb the State, or Elude the Law? nay, was not the Education of Papiſts children by Proteſtants offered to you? And much more of this kind: all this had none of the Magne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick vertue, to draw you together. After this, can to minde His Majeſtres Meſſage from <hi>Nottingham,</hi> when he Foot was only on the way, the hand not lifted up, for no ſtroak was ſtruck, but men Marching only towards this unnaturall and Civill Warre, how doth His Majeſty preſſe for a Treaty, to procure the peace of the Kingdom, what doth he offer for it, <hi>To call in his Proclamations, to take downe his Standard; if the like might be done by his two Houſes?</hi> After a Battel, in the firſt, ſecond, and third Treaties, how endeavour'd he to ſtanch the bloud, how in all theſe did he make great condeſcentions, whilſt the Commiſſioners from the two Houſes were Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſed to afford no Compliance, ſo as neither he, nor his party can ſurely looſe this comfort, that this War was by all meanes declined by Him; That his part in it, hath been the defence of the ancient and knowne Lawes of the Kingdom, whil'ſt thoſe that were againſt him, had nothing to pretend, but a Liberty to introduce new ones, and ſuch as ſuited more with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of their Crimes they had run into, then any waies the good of this people. It is, muſt needs be now, His great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:99939:5"/>that though many of thoſe Rights He hath parted with, and ſince offered, are ſo veſted in him, That he might juſtly have inſiſted to have maintained them. Yet the quiet of his people ſo far prevailed with him, above his owne inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt. Their ingratitude cannot rob him of that inward inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, nor his owne late adverſe fortune (which begins with him, but I am afraid will end with the Kingdom in generall) deprive him of the tranquillity of mind, which die former mentioned Acts, Offers, and late Meſſages yeelds to him.</p>
            <p>What have you fought for all this while? did you not ſtill pretend it was to have Him come up to His Parliament? why doe you then reject that offer? Eſpecially accompanied with the offer of a ſecure <hi>Militia,</hi> Satisfaction in the buſineſſe of <hi>Ireland;</hi> Conſideration of the Publique Debts of His Scots Subjects, Citty of <hi>London</hi> and others; The Government of the Church, according to the beſt daies of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> and King <hi>James,</hi> with full Liberty for the eaſe of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, who will not communicate in that Service eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by Law; And likewiſe for the free and publique uſe of the <hi>Directory,</hi> to ſuch as ſhall deſire to uſe the ſame; To give content in the choyce of the Lord Admirall, and Officers of State and others, with many Reaſons as well as Profeſſions of his confidence of a good accord; And laſtly, of disbanding His Armies, and ſlighting His Garriſons, &amp;c. I know your obvt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous reply; I but this was late, this was neceſſitated. Not late, for from the beginning you ſee how much was offered, had He met with any compliance, at leaſt, ſuch a one as might have ſatisfied Him what He parted with, ſhould not have been turned to His and His Peoples harme, but ſecurity, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly they had had more, and that ſooner: Beſides, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what was pretended too, was another mans Right, and which of us, without more reluctance and delay, would not have deferred the granting more to them, to whom ſo much gave ſo ſlender ſatisfaction. I perceive the laſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to His Majeſty, is a negative to all His deſires and offers, and referres all to Propoſitions to be ſent. How can I hope they will be reaſonable, when your party hath been ſo unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:99939:6"/>in their rejecting His Majeſties Meſſages? How can I think they are trully meant, that have been ſo long deferred? I know not which party prevailes moſt with you; but I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid it's too true what I have heard a great Independent ſaid lately to a Confident of his, That there was two things they muſt pretend, which they would never doe; The one was, to ſet up the Presbytery, the other to ſend down Propoſitions; Or if they meant the laſt, it muſt be reſerved for a ſeaſon, when they will have a prevailing Army to back their unreaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and inſolency. Ah Sir! doth your party pretend the Law and ſo forget it, what is become of the Statute that forbids all men to come up with force to Parliament, was it not that nothing might either be, or ſeem to be Coerc't there; what is become of the great ſecurity he Subject had againſt the King, and by the King? Againſt the King, That no Law could be made but their conſent muſt firſt be had by the King: That no prevailing part in one or both Houſes, could make a Law, no not an Order without His conſent, who was firſt plac'd by God over them, Then whoſe Perſonall experience in Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment (or if a Minor His Councell) was likely to know beſt, what ſuited with the publick good. Am I (Sir) any whit the freer that the King cannot but the two Houſes may (nay after they have driven diverſe of their Members from them) make a Law at their Pleaſure? Am I (Sir) the freer Subject, he King can not preſſe me, the Two Houſes may, The King cannot uſe Martiall Law, the two Houſes may, The King cannot impoſe on my Eſtate, the two Houſes may, The King cannot make other crimes Treaſon then thoſe mentioned in the Statutes, the two Houſes may, nay, may make them none; And others not mentioned there to be Treaſon for as a Dilem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma muſt lye upon the Subjects lives and good? If the King prevaile, the Statutes and Lawes too condemne them; if the Two Houſes, their Declarations and Ordinances riſe up in place of Lawes againſt them What am I the better the King ſwears to <hi>Magna Charta</hi> and the <hi>Petition of Right,</hi> if neither of theſe be to be obſerved by the Houſes? If you Anſwer: yes but they'l doe you no harme, they are of your own body
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:99939:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>Pray tell me, may not I as juſtly ſay, my Head will not Harme me, as my hand: Is it in nature, a man cannot hurt himſelfe, ſure it is nor, we have caily enperience of Felons and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlayers of themſelves. And I am ſure there is more of tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and bowells of an Individuall man to his own body, then there is of a repreſentative body to the body repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: I cannot hurt my ſelfe but I muſt feele, I may another, and be the better for it, warme my ſelfe by the burning my Neighbours houſe. God grant that at this day (though the Kings party are not very guilty of it) <hi>Divitiae pro criminibus non habeantur,</hi> that ſome honeſt men eſtates make them not Delinquents; That the ſence of the guilt of one Party, make not the ſame men ſo rigid to inflict puniſhment upon another, and ſo flatter themſelves, or at leaſ t ſatisfie the Vulgar, Juſtice is done, when like the Cuſtome in the education of Princes, the Page is whipt for the Princes fault. The Innocent is pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht and the Offend or ſcapes.</p>
            <p>Sir, I will conclude all. <hi>Ne glorietur accinctus ae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ut diſcin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus,</hi> Preſume not on the Kings weakneſſe (it led you into the Warre) nor your own ſtrength, it may faile you before you come to your journey's end. While you may, temper your ſucceſles by wiſdome, to a dutifull compliance with your Soveraigne, Let your heart ſmite you, you purſue His life ſo violently. <hi>Zimti</hi> had no Peace, and <hi>Zadock</hi> that preſu???|med all he did was by the ſpirit, found <hi>Micaiah</hi> told him true, That he ſhould find it otherwiſe, when he ſhould flye into the inner Parler to ſave himſelfe. The Canon of Scripture muſt be the Rule, the Spirit is to be tryed by the doctrine, not the doctrine by the Spirit: No though an Angell (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Tutelary to a Presbyterian or Independent) bring it, you have Chriſts word for it, <hi>He that takes the Sword ſhall periſh by it,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 26.52.</note> Periſh not only by being killed, but periſh, (I am loath to write it) Everlaſtingly for killing. Were your quarrell juſt, your mannaging of it ought to be more dutifull to your Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors, more mercifull to your Brethren, you ſhould love the Peace of the Land, more then the purſuit of a few: <hi>Non hoe tantum respicite quas ob cauſas paenas ſitis exacturi, ſed &amp; qui
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:99939:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſint, de quibus ſumenda ſit paena, Qui not ipſi, &amp; quis juſtus pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narum modus.</hi> Remember who you are, and who we are. Remember he that ſlayes an Innocent man haſtens his glory, and his own judgement: Leave off therefore, more for your own ſakes then ours, to be cruell. Think with what unrem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered Morter you build, How many forc'd into you, and not of you, are among you: How many from you: How many of you that cement not together, and leave to deſtroy your firme and ancient foundations, your King and Church, ſo may we once againe ſee the Structures of our Temples and Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-Halls repaired, The King on His Throne, and every man ſitting under his owne Vine.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>This from Your</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
